All right. Uh good afternoon everyone.
My name is Horge Gonzalez. I am the
medical psilocybin program manager and
so welcome to the meeting today and that
is this meeting is uh will be uh chaired
by is chaired by Desbda and she will um
introduce herself in just a moment. But
I want to remind everyone that this
meeting is going is recorded and so uh
please keep all language appropriate and
I will put that reminder in the chat and
with that Desba will you please uh take
the time to introduce yourself and
begin.
>> Yeah. Um my name is Desba. Thank you all
for being here. Um, we have a tall order
[laughter] to fulfill soon. Um, but
before we begin that, I did have an
update that we got just recently from
um, Dominic. We are going to be meeting
with the tribal liaison soon. Um, I know
that some have been asking how um, we're
working with the tribes and they
understand that it is very important. We
also hopefully will be having um some
presentations from grassroots efforts um
in as far as like outreach and education
next month. We're trying to get that set
up. I did try to get another
presentation in at the last minute today
um which I'll talk a little bit about.
Um but that was unfortunately not able
to to happen. Um, but I think it's kind
of gives a little bit of context for
this idea of working with tribes,
working with indigenous groups in New
Mexico, things that have not worked out
in other um, uh, states and possibly
what might actually be coming ahead down
the pipeline for other places. Um, but
yeah, so I'm really happy about that.
Um, things are moving along. uh we have
some other uh conversations going on in
the other committees if you are not
aware of them I'm not exactly sure all
who is here
from other
places
see a few a few of you [laughter]
um yeah and so we're working with uh
right now we're working with uh training
and education and getting some final um
language and considerations for those
regulations uh recommendations
recommendations to be sent to the bigger
board for discussing so that we can then
move them on to the department of
health. So for the few of you who may or
may not um be too aware, we have these
committees that discuss all of the
things that we need to um in in detail
as much as possible. Then we can vote or
recommend to the bigger uh psilocybin
board advisory board where we all
discuss what we has what has happened in
the committees and once we agree on
those then we can then send those
recommendations to the department of
health and then they turn it um into
legal ease and government language do
some magic to turn all of the kind of
lay terms that we have and trying to
figure out the definitions and where
those meet has been a little tricky um
because we all have different broad
definitions of of some things. So, I
just kind of wanted to point that out
and keep that in mind. Um that's been
sort of like the process. Um so, this
isn't all just like what we say here is
final. That's not the case. things go up
for discussion and then even when they
do get to the department of health as
this program continues we will need to
be updating certain languages certain
clauses sentences paragraphs according
to the needs of the program as far as my
understanding and Dominic is free to
[laughter]
chime in if if that's not correct um but
the task that we have for this
particular committee I want to say is um
we have a lot considerations to to think
about. We have a lot a lot of
considerations. We cannot accommodate
every single one. Um we have to kind of
essentially find the one most common
denominator
um and start there to be able to provide
um this particular pathway in the scope
and frame of medical psilocybin
according to the recommendations and the
rules that we have where we are looking
at dosages. We're looking at um care
prior to being able to be able to be a
patient for the use of medical
psilocybin as well as the entire
journey not the not the psychedelic
journey but the journey of the patient
through the system. So from you know
assessment to getting involved um to
having treatments to integration
sessions etc. and then what that looks
like afterwards. You know, where does
say the government care end essentially
and what looking to see what that is. So
there's a lot of steps involved. There
is um this like the screening idea of
getting the person involved. Who who are
we targeting? Who are the people that
are going to be the first uh patients in
this treatment program starting at the
beginning of the year? We're going to be
I think at the end of the year we're
going to be finding what we're locking
in those um recommendations of what that
looks like. So then these people and it
may be a limited number of people um can
start these trials and the important
thing about that is the scientific idea
behind it at least and all this is in my
understanding is that regardless of the
few just like I'm just throwing a number
this is not the number 10 people or 100
people
it's important to make sure that all of
the steps and the protocols and
everything is followed through. so that
we can be able to say, "Okay, this is
what worked and also the things that we
might be able to figure out that need
improvement for the future." But in
order to get there, we need to come up
with a number. We need to come up with
some criteria as to who is starting
first. Um, I just finished watching The
Odyssey and they drew lots. I don't
think we need to draw lots in this
particular case. we need to come up with
some actual uh criteria
um that would allow people of the most
need and it may
may not be what everyone thinks is the
most needed um but we need to we need to
start somewhere. So, so first off, um
what we had discussed
last time
was this idea of starting at um
financial need,
the financial need of a person. And this
is all this is statewide,
right? There's a lot to hold on to here
as far as like the different variables.
Um,
and so where one community that is more
rural than another,
the living wage or however it costs to
live there might be less or more. We
need to kind of just have like a basic
general number to start with and say
that anyone below making below this
amount of money is someone that we're
going to consider as the most um
forgive me for using the wrong language.
You can always chime in in the chat and
help me to use a better better language.
um someone who's in most need of this
medicine financially
because these treatments cost money.
Everything costs money from paying the
uh propagation cultivation to the
testing to packaging it to transporting
it the gas that's involved with that to
getting it to the uh facilitator to the
facilitation of the process to the
patient and the ongoing treatment. All
of that is time and they always say that
uh time is money. Um so we at this point
don't know the exact cost of that chain
from growing to transportation to
facilitator to patient what that could
be. It could be and we we're looking at
different models in like Oregon and
Colorado what what has happened there
and what's going to be happening here.
Um,
and so
we just kind of have to start out though
regardless of what that number ends up
being, whether it costs
$1,000, more than $1,000, but whether it
costs like $1,000 to
$10,000 for the transportation of this
single dose, etc. Um, we need to just
kind of come up with a number. And I
know that this is just a long- winded um
way of saying we have this slide here
that Jorge has put up where we decided
lastly to come up with 200% poverty
federal poverty level. What that means
is that the federal poverty poverty
level at this time currently for 2026 or
2025 is 18,000. So 200% of that would
mean that anyone who makes with a family
of one, anyone who makes $31,000 and 900
$920
or below
would be then considered um
needing uh financially needing
for the for the medicine. And anyone who
has a family of two that household in
the poverty line increases to 43,284
size of a family of four etc. it raises
to 66,000. So this means that anyone
66,000 for a family of four or below
would be considered eligible for
participation as a patient for the
medical psilocybin program. And this is
not to not to say that we're looking at
any other criteria other than just the
income. Um Jorge, did you want to add
something in?
>> Uh you explained it. Uh yeah, thank you
Desa and and attendees for the
committee. Um there uh we presented a
tiered eligibility chart uh in June uh
with different numbers as far as the
know that that we thought the committee
had mentioned and so we created that
present Leslie Peterson presented that
last month and and this is where it
landed. the committee uh had said 200%
of the federal poverty level. And so we
just put those together uh created a
visual here so that folks could
understand what that what that means uh
as far as the the size of the household
and what that income would be for them
to be eligible and that so if someone
was above any of these income amounts
they would not be eligible. So yeah, the
the committee had had uh recommended not
having that tiered approach and so
that's why there's only one income level
here for each of those uh size of the
households. And that's all I wanted to
add.
>> Thank you.
>> And I thank you. Um and I want to say
just like is anybody have any questions
up to this point? This is definitely
open for a conversation because I know
that before
we have a lot of concerns. We did if
anyone was not here prior to um the uh
slides that we had with um Hanifo of
Washington and Denali Wilson they did
also provide different you know models
and methods for kind of looking at this
problem um this challenge and so yeah
let's go um Ian I think I saw your hand
pop up
I don't know if Ian's mic is enabled or
not, but
>> your mic isn't enabled. And you talk
when you're ready.
Hi, can you hear me?
>> Yes, now we can.
>> Hi. Sorry, my computer was acting up.
Um, yeah, I was just curious, um, and
maybe you guys had discussed this in the
last meeting. I couldn't make it, but
one of another area we might be able to
look at instead of just federal poverty
level is just the amount of cash on
hand. uh depending on which you know
study you look at between 40 to 60% of
Americans live paycheck to paycheck and
so while they might not be fully
encompassed by the federal poverty level
if they have no cash on hand they
obviously can't receive services um so I
was just curious if that had been
discussed or if it um I don't know just
what the committee thought
>> yeah I think that the term term cash on
hand I don't think was explicitly used
but I think we did talk about um God and
I someone has to help me here but I'm
thinking in terms of financial aid for
like colleges and in um we had uh
extenduating circum circumstances or
things like that that would uh be taken
into consideration right so what you
actually and I think there's an actual
term for it adjusted not adjusted gross
income, but it was like adjusted
something or other that we looked at and
we were considering. Um, not that we
didn't discuss it, but it was it was in
that realm. So, I think I saw Greg or
Brenda their hand pop up.
>> Brenda,
>> Brenda, your mic's enabled.
>> Uh, yeah, I just put it in the chat. A
sliding fee for um people's income. Uh I
think uh that's what uh some therapists
do. Uh like myself, we like if somebody
says, you know, uh you know, uh going
through my insurance is is is
kind of wonky, can I just uh can we go
by what my income is and and do a
sliding fee of that? Um
uh if that would work. So I just wanted
to throw it out there. Thank you.
>> Yeah. And um thank you Brenda. I think
Dominic [clears throat] put it in the
chat. It's adjusted modified income and
they use the same thing as well when
considering um students for uh
scholarships or financial aid. financial
aid primarily at colleges and I don't
know what in other what ways that's used
for um
but that would you know taking into
other considerations like you just
bought a new car or your house burned
down or you know some some other
extenduating circumstances or some other
considerations you just had a surgery so
now you're on the you know you have a
hundred and some thousand bill so things
like that which would definitely impact
you know a person's ability to Okay. So
that that was being taken into um not
not taken into consideration that was
discussed in the last meeting. Um and
then I see something else in the chat.
Let's see here.
Uh
jump to newest. Okay. Question. So would
the finances for this program be geared
more toward the financially challenged
and not the degree of the disability or
behavioral issue? Are there levels of
the behavioral diagnosis or referrals
that you would also include to determine
the help? And if the physician
recommends medical psilocybin and the
patient is above the poverty level, does
the patient self-pay or does the
insurance cover it? Okay, good question.
I'm going to start at the bottom of that
question really quickly because we need
to kind of again juggle and hold on to
these things. So, when we're talking
about the 200% federal poverty level
needs met, let me throw this term in
there, needs met. Um, we're also taking
into consideration
after
insurance, after every other potential
uh discount, let's just call it discount
or consideration, right? So, like your
explanation of benefits. I'm sorry I'm
throwing around these terms loosely.
please forgive me. But as far as like
you're you're seeing like the benefits
of okay, you have your discount, you
have your insurance, and now you're on
the line for $300 of your dose.
But for me especially, a $300 dose is
still I can't do that, right? So that's
where this 200% federal poverty level
will come in is that we're going to look
at as a household of two,
do I make $43,000 or more or less? And
where do I fall into that? Let's just
say for the example of this, yes, I do
fall at 43,200.
So then I would be eligible as far as my
understanding to be uh taking advantage
of this particular program
because I fall in that federal poverty
level after insurance after any other
discounts after anything else. I still
cannot pay the $300 price tag for the
psilocybin. I have I have gone through
um assessment deems that I have a
medical issue that is um as a go as a
green light for medical psilocybin
um and I meet all these different
criteria. So to answer that last
question, it's it's it's a discounted
rate first. Then we how do we how do we
cover and meet the need of that person
at that price tag where they're still
out of pocket for like the $300?
That's where this program is going to
come in and meet the need of the
patient. Um I'll get back to the rest of
the question, but in you have your hand
raised.
>> Yeah. So, uh, just a followup. Is that
200% of the federal poverty level the
like floor for when it starts tapering
off or is that the cap of the end of the
taper? So, basically, are we covering
100% of the session if they're at 200%
or is that like a reduced amount?
Dominic may have a better answer, but it
is my understanding that at if we just
went with just this slide and nothing
else, right? We weren't doing the
adjusted uh modified income, we weren't
taking any other things into
consideration. It was just this slide.
To me, it would be that yes, it would it
would, you know, pay for that 300.
But I think that's a really good
question because
not everybody this is I kind of love
this and I'm also very horrified to find
out that as we're thinking through this
problem you know someone else is going
to have a price tag for 500 someone else
may have a price tag for 200 right so
this is this is where you know is is
there like a strict like $300 cap um
[laughter] magic
All right. Um I'm going to go ahead and
let Dominic answer something because he
was has his hand raised.
>> Yeah. So So one thing I just want to
clarify is that um what we're just
showing on the screen was just because
the questions were coming up in the last
meeting um about what this looks like.
What does 200% of the poverty level look
like? That's the only reason we're
showing it is because it's what came up
last time. Just like in the previous
meeting, we were showing those others uh
levels of income in the poverty level uh
calculations because it's what had come
up in the previous one. What we really
need for this committee to do at this
point is to make recommendations as to
what you think it should look like in
order to go ahead and help patients and
what you think the distribution of that
funds, how that should be determined. So
this is just what we're showing on the
screen is just what had brought been
brought up the last time and just
showing it for information purposes.
Nothing actually has been recommended at
this point as to what it should be or
shouldn't be. It's just these are just
some numbers for people to have as a
starting point to sort of make uh these
kinds of comments. And so what I would
really say is by the end of this meeting
to have one or two recommendations as to
what it should look like for how we
distribute the equity fund to those who
need it.
>> And on that um
we had before like two or three meetings
ago we had looked at 300%.
Based on the fact I'm going to really
confuse everybody based on the fact that
we were kind of looking at at Santa Fe
Um,
and
it's it's uh and that's why I'm saying
this is for the state. There has to be
some kind of consensus amongst the
state. Whereas, you know, Los Alamos
County and they're really high rate of
living. Santa Fe is next and then I
don't know who follows down beyond that.
But then you also have to look at the
counties that are the lowest uh levels
of uh living wage etc.
uh cost of living and catch everybody.
And whereas it might seem
disadvantageous to one particular
area or you know it it just um
we all re we all realize that nobody can
live off of really $31,000.
It's just impossible across statewide.
It's like I think at that point you have
to be a renunciate. Um, but that's just
kind of where we're that's why we're
looking at the 200%.
Um, it's just a starting point. What
would be I guess the least most amount
of income that we are saying yes, we
will help 100%
perhaps um after all of the discounts,
after insurance, right? And I think that
that's what we're just kind of looking
at. So with the other recommendation
like say we just nailed a 200% 300%
whatever it is starting point based on
finances
then we can start looking at all the
other aspects of it which would possibly
be an adjusted modified income. Um what
would we look at next?
uh in addition to how else we would look
at the funds, one of the things that I
will echo as far as
uh a comment that was made previously by
Senator Seinborn was, you know, really
wanting this fund to be able to provide
as much
uh
financial
can't think of the word. I'm so sorry.
but in order to be able to take care of
as many people as possible.
But also realizing that, you know,
$630,000
isn't really all that much when it comes
to the number of people that we're
having to take care of given a lot of
unknown variables. And one, like I
pointed out, was the cost of a of a
single dose
for a person.
And how many doses would this person
particularly need? Is are they going to
be limited to one? Is it going to be you
know is this person going to be able to
have let's just say a return on
that one dose after three whole
sessions? Is it going to be five? How
much of each of those sessions? You
know, and that's where all of this stuff
comes in. But primarily it would be for
primarily would be for the medical
psilocybin itself because everything
else would be essentially could
potentially be covered by regular
insurance for therapy. Right? So that's
why we're just really looking at the
cost of the treatment and dosage and the
travel and expenses and how is that
being how is that being recovered? Is it
through the facilitator themselves? Are
they being reimbursed? Um so then that
there's all these questions. So I say we
needed someone who is a mathematician to
kind of come up with a formula um to be
able to explain where all these
different variables for the cost of a
dose would be for this one particular
person at this one particular time. Um
okay we have one person with a hand up
think in did you still want to say
something or is that a leftover?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, I was actually just
going to say um thank you Dominic for
clarifying. So, those are just the
numbers that we could work with. Um
given that the median income in New
Mexico is I can't remember if it's 64
65,000
um
we could adopt the 300 200% and still
get most of the people around that are
below average income. or we could try
the 300% and then taper off. My concern
with that is that when you have so many
patients, the fund loses money very
quickly. Um I think if we started let's
say 200% and then um at 250 we cover
let's say 90 and then taper down slowly
so that we would cover less as you got
more income instead of having like a
hard, you know, just cut. Oh, you made a
dollar too much this year. Sorry. um
just to try to avoid that cuz I know
that that is a real struggle. Um and
then like just as a rough comparison um
I'm a patient I suffer with PTSD um
without insurance um
my medication is over $1,500 a month. So
I am very acutely aware of how expensive
the medical system can be. Um but I do
believe that if we are working to
help these lower income patients and we
are working to ensure that um economies
of scale can really help these
manufacturers as well as the patients um
then we can help to reduce that cost and
especially with the commitment from the
department to not have um at least for
now um at the beginning of the program
licensing fees. I think that will help
to drastically reduce the amount of
liability it takes to start a practice
and that should hopefully lower the
costs. Um, but again, like you said, we
have so many unknown variables that
we're going to have to take a leap of
faith no matter what the end
goal is. Like adjusted modified income,
great. that's income I believe after
like housing expenses and and living
expenses. Um
but
when we do whatever we end up taking it
is going to be just kind of a leap of
faith and of of hoping cuz we
I know of many people who are interested
but that doesn't mean like I know how
many patients to expect like especially
as the program continues to develop and
we continue to get you know right now
unless your friend is uh involved in
clinical research or is in the
underground market. Um I would really
say unless they're in clinical research,
they're not going to have the same style
of experience and so they may not be
drawn to the medical system in general
if they're not um okay if they're not
happy with the medical system in
general. So, I just think it's important
that we, you know, when we take this
consideration, just recognize that we're
not going to have the final number, um,
but that we have the ability to review
and revise once those numbers become
more concrete.
>> Yeah, that's why the whole idea of
variable. And we did have a bit of a
discussion kind you brought up two
points. One of them was this idea of a
tiered um um model where
you know at the 200%
you know then once we have fulfilled
uh x number of people at that place and
so no more applicants at like a certain
time frame right like I'm just saying
I'm not saying that this is what
actually happened but 200% given a
six-month period we have you know all of
those patients that are still applying
for the program. Um,
and you know, let's just say that it it
it there's no more applicants at the
200% mark, then we would go to a
different tiered approach where you
know, and it would be kind of like a
flowing system. I think that that's a
little too much math. Um, but that to me
would be something that would make the
most sense in terms of especially not
knowing how many people are actually
willing and wanting to go through these.
Um,
and then that way that the money is
still utilized, is still going through
and is still available as we're
continuing to go higher up in the scale.
So from 200 to 250 to 300%.
Um, and it may still be able to meet
that, you know, like at somewhere
there's just enough money for the person
who has 300% poverty line and is still
able to get in. I think another thing to
be considering which also was brought up
was um
kind of a I I did not get to read all of
Jim's um comment but the first part of
it was you know the we it did come up in
the last meeting about treatment
resistant um therapies you know and also
this idea of the assessment and
treatment the pre-intake portion of it
you know this is not considering people
who are looking for micro doing or so
forth. Um this is uh we're looking for
people who you know at the one gram
point of a dose right and beyond um up
until this point. Now if there was a
scale of you know one to 10 zero being
micro dose level and then there's that
sweet spot between four five and six
level of yes does this person seem like
they would most likely be able to get
the benefits of you know say three the
therapy sessions or however long it is.
But then we also have the people who are
in the you know 10 n and eight section
or you know that this might necessarily
need more therapy sessions and this is
not part of the program. This was kind
of where I was thinking as far as what
to kind of look at. I again am not privy
to how this is being um metered out but
it still goes back to this idea of what
Jim raised is like we don't want it to
fail at the same time we not only the
program itself right doing the uh being
responsible to the program and helping
it thrive and survive and support uh the
people that have put all their time and
effort into providing this medicine but
also to the patients themselves. We
don't want to be dismissive of the vast
array of how much people need, but on a
financial level, we do want to make sure
that this program continues on into the
future and may or may not be able to
gain more funding and we might be able
to um provide more at a later time, but
we have to be able to be judicious in
how we're um figuring out. And there is
a little bit of
uh you know we can't be voyers. We can't
you know anticipate the future. But I
feel like trying to find just that
little middle spot where we can be of
most help to the most number of people.
And the most number of people it could
be 10 people. It could be 100 people.
I'm sure that you know it would be
better if we reached a 100 people or
even a thousand people. um that would be
much more that would be better. But then
that goes back into how much does each
of these uh doses and these treatments
cost
and of course how many people are
actually knocking down and beating down
the doors to get a part of this program
which I know that is not everybody's cup
of tea but it is a very specific pathway
for the that kind of person. Um, and in
a conversation that we had, yes, it this
is not necessarily all, you know, having
a hike out in the woods and, you know,
singing songs and on the drums. It's
not. It could be
somewhere down the line, but this is
really just kind of like a doorway and a
pathway and a first start for the people
who really actually feel more
comfortable in a clinical type setting
where they feel like they know that
there is somebody who knows CPR where
they know that somebody is is there and
that's because that's their norm. and
we're looking to make sure that we are
finding ways to to to care for as many
people financially in this particular
way as we can. Um, Greg, you have your
hand up.
Um just to touch on um
Hanifa's question here about
[clears throat] Medicaid. I think it
would be interesting to kind of like
trace that conversation and I know
we are amongst the process of discovery
on that and there's a lot of unknowns.
Um, I think it's interesting that if we
land the Medicaid, which I think we are
hoping and expecting to do, then a huge
chunk of the total cost for the people
in this category is already going to be
diverted.
So the the co remaining costs being the
things that insurance won't cover
and that being like the dosing day
whether it's the therapy around the
dosing day or the cost of the medicine
or whatever that's all to be discovered
but I think
one of the questions that I had in that
conversation about insurance and
hopefully there's somebody here that
wants to get into this or we can get
into it in the future. Is are we
considering the cost of treatment being
like similar to cancer like with
chemotherapy where it's like the entire
single it's like a single payment on a
super bill for the all of the different
uh events inside the container of the
PAT event.
I think that's the whole thing.
PAT
>> psychedelic assisted therapy.
And yeah, I agree it's not for everyone.
I'm probably not going to like I mean
it's not for me. Although I am severely
depressed and I would gladly do it for
science. [snorts]
Sign me up. I'm on Medicaid. [laughter]
>> On the note, just kind of briefly just
to kind of maybe get our heads out of
the headache that this is producing is
just, you know, I think that there is
something to be said about the therapy
portion of and looking at some other
models of the facilitators and and
witnessing slides and presentations and
um events where facilitators have talked
about um their work and what they've
done. Um you know there there's there is
a great amount of wow that's looks like
it's actually you know to to see to see
to see like in the real-time events of
working with someone who is a therapist
and having that person essentially
literally or metaphorically hold your
hand in this particular place but have
that kind of and I want to say it the
clinical background of you know what
does this mean? However, um I think is a
very fascinating and to me that's just
like
it it looks enticing um to be able to
have to go through that model of not
only do you get like the breakthrough of
the medicine working in itself. Not only
do you have just like the natural space,
but then you have the added benefit of
someone who is able to kind of help
guide you through that in a in a place
that someone is is very familiar with
the inner workings of the mind. um from
that approach. I just I think it's
really fascinating and it to me looks
insanely beneficial of a of of something
that I would definitely you know tell
people yes you know this would be
possibly something for you.
Um okay.
All right. So let's uh Hanifha says I
think 200% is a good place to start and
I recommend if people who do not have
insurance by which any part of the care
model
is covered would be 100% covered. Um we
have another comment from Katherine. If
Medicaid pays for the service at least
for providers and facilities you cannot
bill the patient for the balance. I
wonder if that will be the same for
medical psilocybin services.
Uh,
I'm not sure what the comment is with
Jim's what a patient discusses as
private. Yes, that is just protocol. It
is all paid. Um, Brenda, you have your
hand up.
>> Thanks, Desbah. I really appreciate you
explaining this the way you are because
it has to be it has to be said in in a
language that we could all understand.
And I think sometimes we get ahead of
ourselves with, you know, um using uh
certain, you know, protocols or ways of
speaking in in a lot of these meetings,
but you're doing a wonderful job with um
explaining this. Um I had a couple of
things that kind of came to mind,
especially with like Medicaid services
and billing and all that. My background
is addiction and I've worked in a lot of
rehabs and so basically how it works is
like for rehabs a lot of people are
there for 30 32 days and that's a very
very expensive program I and it's um and
there's a lot of hands-on deck with with
teams uh you know you have uh you have a
cook you have um uh CSWs you have uh
therapists on board. You have nurses,
you have uh uh medication, uh you have
and it's all it it's all in one uh all
under one roof. So why can't um you
know, insurance pay the same way as I
don't expect you to answer this
question, but you know, why can't
insurance pay it like it does a rehab?
uh it's only a one day thing or maybe
you know twice a year where someone
comes in uh they've got their therapist
they've got a staff of of people there
and uh you know we're look we're looking
at a clinical uh environment not so much
you know being out in a cabin or
anything because this is the medical
model. Um so and and just having your
your uh clinician there there's your
your who's been trained in in uh
psilocybin
uh you know you have uh the medication
that was transported there and it it's
it's locked up for safekeeping and um
it's uh administered and you're sitting
there with your your your your client
and uh they're you know they're being
you know um observed. you're there to,
you know, help them with anything that
that they may need. And so, uh, then
after 6 to 8 hours, uh, they're done.
And, uh, you know, the you as the
therapist would be meeting them
afterwards for any integration or
anything anything else that comes along
and you carry on with your therapy uh,
treatment um, along with the uh,
psilocybin experience. So I'm I'm kind
of looking at this through through that
lens because um I think that would be a
much better uh model to look at than you
know we're we're you know trying to
imagine what this would be like. But I
think uh looking at like what a rehab
model uh looks like would be um
something to kind of follow through on
and that um it possibly could save a lot
of costs instead of like someone being
in a facility for uh the 30 days they're
only there for one day or one and a half
days depending on you know what time
they are going in or maybe uh the
protocol has changed. They need to stay
there for a day and a half or whatever.
But that would cut uh a lot of cost just
um there uh just having uh you know your
therapist there and um it I don't know
how much uh a doctor would be need to be
there or a nurse to be there but just um
maybe uh you know there's other people
in the facility that are on on staff. So
I there's a lot of ways to kind of look
at this and try to create some type of
um of cost cutting type of thing and
also too groups you know uh I'm sure
later on there probably could be
possible uh group therapy as well and
then um you know as a therapist myself
I've done pro bono as well. So these are
like kind of like some of these ideas
that are kind of floating around there
in my head. So I just wanted to put that
out there, you know, um for people to
kind of look at and see if this is this
is
something that could be um looked at and
thought about.
>> Yeah, thank you Brenda. Um, something
that you said while you were explaining,
something that came to mind was when you
said rehab model was just, you know,
what the cost would look like for the
day. And I hope the department of health
is taking lots of notes. Um,
because the thing that came to mind was
it would be nice if we had universal
healthcare in New Mexico. Um, and
everything just all the the price tag on
everything was just the same. And I
don't know if that was something that
was already discussed prior to or it's
like a known that I'm not aware of it.
Um, but everything having the same price
tag, right? Every therapist charging
$300 for a session, you know, for for
let's just say when I say a session, I
mean for specifically the the uh
psilocybin treatment therapy session,
that specific one where we know for
certain that that is not going to be
covered um by insurance. um as far as I
know. And so if it just has that
singular nobody can charge above, nobody
can charge below, it is just the $300,
then boom, we can take care of um
however many 300 goes into 630,000
and that can all just be across the
board and then we have that known for
that particular thing. But again, back
to this idea of how much, you know,
everyone's insurance is going to be
different. Some people pay zero co-pays,
some people have to pay 35, some people
have to pay 15,
you know, and so all of these uh
different variables are going to then,
you know, move that amount of need met
for the medicine and how much money is
going to be done. My need met is $300.
Um ex-husband's is like $200. Friend
down the street has $100 need met. Um
maybe we're all around the same, you
know, income bracket, but each of them
are going to be different because each
of us are on different insuranceances.
So
I'm like, that guy doesn't have a kid.
Why is he only paying $100? I've got a
kid, but I have to pay $200. And they're
basing off the 300 for ex-husband or
whatever, you know, is because of their
past job, and now they're unemployed,
you know. So I totally get to me I'm I'm
not sure. So that's why we're coming
back at this like where do we start with
the with the federal poverty so that we
can just have a place to say um without
knowing everyone's insurance co-pays
without knowing how much their uh
discounts are going to be from whatever
you know Blue Cross Blue Shield
Presbyterian or whatever else is going
to be taking care of the therapies. We
just need to worry about the cost of the
medicine session and what does that look
like and how much of it are we going to
to cover. I would ask for anybody from
the department to say that I am talking
crazy. Um but this is what I'm thinking
about when I'm thinking of all of the
massive variables that we have to look
at. Um and to your point, Brenda, also
we did um Hanifeha and Denali did
provide um a series of presentations
several weeks ago, several meetings ago
about
individual group therapies and what that
would look like um as far as like, you
know, they would be more cost beneficial
if we were doing groups and it would
also depend on how many sessions from
from assessment to um the end of
integration. Um and and that was brought
up and yes, group therapies would be
possibly more
costcutting, but also I think that at
the end of the day, the presentation we
got was it wasn't going to be by much
essentially.
Um, one other thing I I just wanted to
say about um, like I I I think you you
hit on something here that uh, you like
just having a set
price or set fee of what a a a therapist
would charge. And um I don't know if
there is
like you know I I I guess what I'm
trying to say is um a therapist can
pretty much charge what they want to
charge within reason. I mean there's no
there is kind of a I think there is kind
of a cap there as far as you know what
they what they can charge. So, um I
think that would be a really great thing
to have. That way it it kind of makes it
a more even playing field. And you know,
uh then you're not going to have a
therapist and say, "Oh, I am the one
that uh I uh give these services to, so
I'm going to charge $500 per hour and uh
this is me." And you know, you don't
want to have any of that. So, I think
having this nice set price for for what
a therapist offers, you know, I I I
think um that's something that um that
also needs to be looked at. But yeah,
like um I really wish I could come to a
lot more of your meetings. It's it just
so happened that I had cancellations
this afternoon.
>> No, no worries. And so I think that um
that you're hitting on a lot of points
here that um you know it's giving the
department of health a lot to to think
about because I think when we went into
this I think we all knew this this was
going to be big but we didn't know how
big this was going to be and that you
know we're all volunteers here and
that's what I want to remind the public
that the the this uh the advisory board.
I don't think any of us are getting paid
for it. We're doing it out of the um you
know, our duty as you know, citizens and
as professionals to try to put together
a program that um that will work for New
Mexico. And yeah, we're gonna we're
looking at Oregon and we're looking at
Colorado. However, we do have a very big
vulnerable pop population here and also
we don't have the resources that Oregon
and Colorado have. So we really have to
kind of uh lock arms together and and
march forward with this as best as we
can with taking into considerations of
of of course income, disability,
uh you know um uh travel uh you know or
or you know and and making sure that the
people that we're um uh that are
licensed are properly trained for um
what we're going to be um doing here.
So, I just wanted to throw that out.
These just thoughts going on in my head
and uh yeah, thank you again, Desma.
>> Yeah. Um no, I think thank you for
bringing all that up. Um Sky Rivers,
let's see. Let me read backwards here.
Sky Rivers, Oregon just doubled their
prices. Sorry to come late. No one
worries about it. Um,
and let's see. Hanifeha recommended that
those that qualify for the TEF that
require multiple medicine sessions are
covered up to three medicine sessions
within 6 months or some specified time.
Um, and then also we're not taking from
Katherine, we're not taking into
consideration premiums. Everyone pays is
different. Yes, I don't think we can
drill down that deep into financials.
Yeah, we can't we can't sit there. I
mean, we can and we can't. Um, and by
that I said we can ask questions, but we
also might be limited in in the answers
that we're able to actually get and or
you know, HIPPA, etc. All kinds of
different laws that are regulations and
we're aware of those. Um, so how do we I
don't want to say work around, but work
with um the unknown. [laughter]
Um, and that's kind of again back to
this idea of thank you Brenda for saying
that. You know, you kind of like this
idea of like if we just had that therapy
session
um with the medicine included, medicine
session is capped at $500 for the dose
and that is given to the provider to pay
for the medicine that they are using.
I'm not a huge fan of the way in which,
you know, we all can decide how much
prices or whatever. Who knows? That's an
opinion. But then that at least I feel
if we just were able to say this is you
cannot charge more for this particular
session for this price for the medicine
itself. But any of the other therapy
sessions, you know, you feel like you
want to charge $100 an hour for one
session. You know, someone else is going
to charge $235, you know, depending on
the length of their um certifications
and knowledge and years, etc.
That's beyond, right? But then how does
that affect
the amount of money that is given for
therapy? Um, and by that I mean if a
whole session for one person is like
comes down to five sessions and each is
at 200
$200.
Uh, sorry I see 10 sessions. 2350 bucks.
No, 23. Sorry. 235.
>> So let's say like someone's session,
someone's total price tag for therapy
including the medicine is $1675.
Then if everybody's was that way, cuz
we're all the same and we all have the
same problems that need to be addressed
in the exact same way and the exact same
length of time, that means we would
possibly be able to cover 376 people.
If if let's just say if a if a person
who was a therapist charged $235
per hour session
for five sessions,
including the $500 price tag on the
medicine. I've just I'm just throwing
numbers out here, people. I'm not I'm
not a wizard. I'm just kind of trying to
get an idea of what that looks like. Um
let's see.
Yeah. 30,000 to 50,000. And I'm Let's
just throw that number in there
divided by 30,000.
So we're if each session just saying
that we were to look at it each session,
each treatment program for one person at
a rehab price tag with the $630,000 that
we have. That would limit us to 21
people.
that would have to meet a certain amount
of criteria and that would be let's just
say 200% poverty level.
That's basically their entire annual 200
times their annual salary.
Um,
and I don't feel like we're getting any
further, but I'm just throwing all of
this information out there. Hopefully,
it's kind of like making sense to you
because it as I'm just keep rambling.
It's making a little bit more sense to
me of how complicated this is. And maybe
I'm making it a little bit more
complicated than it needs to be. I did
hear um in say that 300% that was like
the initial kind of place we came to. Um
I believe Chris and Senator Steinborg
said that we probably should lower it a
little bit. So that's why it's back up
for debate. Is it 300% poverty level
that we should begin with and then work
our way down? Um, by that I mean that's
the cap for now. Um, that we're working
with those people that will meet 100%
their need met after discounts after
everything else and that their cost of
their medicine is X amount or do we
lower it to 200%. Is that the starting
point? We're at the 4:00 hour mark.
[laughter]
Um, does anybody have any other
uh information? And then to kind of to
Skye's point, you know, about the the
the number and I'm not sure if it was
this specifically,
but um
you know, the cost of the medicine and
being able to make sure that we do take
care of our propagation, our New Mexico
uh propagation and cultivation people
and you know, is that are we able to
make sure that they too are part of this
equation? Because it's not just about,
you know, the therapist making money.
It's really about the energy that
everyone is putting into this process.
It's about the person who is seeking the
medicine, putting the energy into
wanting the help and seeking relief, to
the person that is providing the
listening ear to be there for them, to
the people who are transporting that the
medicine to the place. To the people who
are doing the testing. and we met these
people and they're amazing people um who
are doing everybody is doing this of
service to the medicine in the hopes
that we can help get everyone back
online.
So I don't want it to sound like you
know somebody's you know making a profit
here and getting you know like not
getting their due. We're all in this
together as far as being in the service
of the medicine from the people who who
gather the spores and you know
put the make magic and the mcelium etc
and harvest praying for it etc. singing
to it whatever happens whatever m magic
happens to getting it to to the person
and then the journey of the person
forward.
So, everyone is putting something into
this in order to get something back out
of it.
Um,
so any other insight?
>> Uh, Jeff has his hand up.
>> Okay, great. Yes.
>> Hey, thanks Dezba. I just uh Sorry,
guys. I don't know if it's live. I just
put it in the into the chat uh because I
thought we were about to run out of
time. Yeah, basically I I know I've been
a party to a lot of the discussion which
has been really great and fascinating. I
think the 200% is probably a good clear
um understandable income level place to
start. Um just my own two cents and is
affordable for the grant program. Um but
I would put that caveat. I think it's
really smart that we're talking about
like what therapy
sessions, if that's the right word, can
be potentially covered from insurance
before and after the before and after
the journey. And so like maybe as a part
of the grant program if we are
checking to see if like
making or I should say making sure that
the the the person doing the journey or
the facilitator that they are not the
facilitator but people working on the
pre and post integration that they are
trying to get it covered. I don't know,
not as a requirement that someone would
have to have be working with somebody
who
is covering it or that it has to be
covered, but that we make that effort to
do that because it'll just obviously
make the money go a lot further. So,
that would be my suggestion 200% and
then encourage that there be a process
for working with the people providing
the services to get as much of it
covered as possible.
That's all I have.
>> Thank you. And then just to kind of
maybe clarify, when you say to work to
get that covered,
it sounds like that the possibility of
potential gaps in the funding where it's
not all met or am I I'm sorry. Do you
mind if you have a minute to clarify
that?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Basically, that's what I'm
saying. I'm saying that um if if uh
you know as opposed to as opposed to a
um
a place a healing center for lack of
putting it a better way comes to the
state and says well we want a grant for
the whole thing including the therapy
before the counseling before and after
the journey that could possibly be
covered by insurance that if we try to
get as much try to encourage that they
they cover as much of it as possible
>> and that way we're only funding the gap.
That's that's exactly what I'm saying.
That'll make the money go a whole lot
further than if we're funding the whole
bill.
>> Got it. And then in that case, I might
have missed where there are grants
available from New Mexico State to
provide for facilitators to help fill
out the gaps. Is that just an idea
that's in the future or is that
something that's available now?
>> No, that's I think part of the equity
fund part of I mean that this fund would
pay I mean we haven't decided it yet but
that in theory this fund would pay for
the entire cost of someone getting
treatment which will be
>> not just the journey but the work before
the journey the integration work after
the journey.
>> Yeah. But if those ser but if those
services are covered by insurance then
basically we that would leave us with
the costs of the medicine itself in the
day of
>> it's not co that's not covered
>> and that again that not that we place
that as a requirement that those things
have to be covered and we will only fund
the day of the journey but that we
somehow encourage it and even require
that they demonstrate that it's not
covered
the pre and post before we will give
them that funding. See what I'm saying?
Someone but if they have insurance and
they've got
I don't know Medicaid covers it, but
that they may be covered. So anyway,
I'll just leave that out there because I
don't know. I mean, there's been
discussion about would it cover it? Can
we get it covered? I just think that's a
super smart way to approach it to make
the money go multiples further. But I
could be completely wrong on this, but
that's just my opinion. I just wanted to
share. So, thanks.
>> Okay. Thank you. Yeah. Thank you,
Senator.
>> Um,
anyone else? [laughter]
I think I think that we, you know, as
far as like we did come up with the
200%, that would be like a good place to
start. Um, I do agree, you know, because
it's come up again. I think there's
something to it. the idea what Ian said
as far as like a tiered um but then that
brings in new information as far as um
like what else do we look at
because
um
because back to Jim's point in the
beginning which is again something that
we had thought brought up earlier was
you know we don't want to have it happen
and this is this is also an unknown an
unknown too as well
but the likelihood and there's
statistics involved I'm sure maybe few
but
you know somebody who is a good
candidate for because of whatever you
know um there might be there might be
financially this person might fit the
criteria but their medical diagnosis,
the criteria they meet may not
necessarily
dictate that they are a good candidate
for the program for the financial um
grant.
So what do we do then? Obviously we
would probably have to have just you
don't meet the criteria.
Um but what are those things? What are
those uh what is the environment the
financial environment that we need to
create in order for someone to have
access to this um from a financial
standpoint and how do we take into
consideration
the outside considerations of diagnosis
type if we do
other criteria such as um
rural area if that was another one. Um,
we don't essentially want this to kind
of be marketed, you know, that there's a
financial uh, money available and
somehow only goes to Santa Fe and
Albuquerque. That would be an incredible
disservice.
How do we then make sure that ensure
that we have everybody from the every
corner of the state have a viable chance
of participating in this program that
needs it both financially, medically,
um,
and what are those other criteria?
Um,
>> that's I see Ian's hand up.
>> Okay. Yeah, Ian.
>> Yeah. Uh, I just wanted to kind of hop
on um what Senator Steinborn was saying
cuz I think it ties into exactly what
you just brought up, which is it's a
it's an incredible disservice um to
because yes, half of our state
population between Albuquerque and Santa
Fe, sure, but that leaves a million
people um that are not in that area. And
so it is incredibly important to me that
we um take care of them. So one of the
options we could look at um and is not
to pay the patient bills directly. is to
say, okay, what if we gave um medically
underserved and rural areas
um we could offer grants through the
fund to say we'll help you construct in
these areas where it would or build out
an existing building where in these
areas where it may be more expensive to
do so um and where the demand doesn't um
justify it instantaneously. And so a lot
of businesses tend to opt out if they
don't get their um instant
gratification. So
I I think it could be an interesting
thing just to kind of look at, but I do
think um the 200% cover everything is a
great place to start. We'll taper up. Um
I think 300% is a way too a little bit
too high. um our median income in this
state would be equal to um 300% which
means about half of our population would
be eligible and while I wish we could
give it to uh half of our population we
would end up um
out of money very very quickly. So I
think there are two uh avenues that we
can explore. I think we're pretty solid
in at least 200 should be covered and
then we'll see about how that exact
taper works and I'm sure the department
will get more information on a tier
around that system. Um but yeah, I just
wanted to throw out the possibility that
yeah, we could potentially in these
underserved areas, um like for instance,
there is a a large patient pool, right?
They're not New Mexicans, but there's a
large patient pool right south of um Los
Cusus and El Paso. They may not be able
to qualify for the equity fund, but we
should still help those communities um
build infrastructure, build um and
support the New Mexicans that are living
there, even if their population, right,
on its own doesn't support it.
>> Thank you, Ann. Um and then you also
brought up another idea. Um it's another
point of you know how how
uh yeah because this is through the
clinicians the the the therapists
um side of it that who know their
populations more
intimately
and you know as I have pointed out
before in the past I come from Espanola
area Rioba County highest opioid
uh uh deaths in the state country. Um
and I can imagine that someone might
feel like yes, this is a place that we
need to to target as far as you know
making sure that we are supporting and
taking care of our people here or even
in Farmington four corners area, Gallup.
Two of those places are where I have
family. Um, and I had a
cousin die of a fentinol overdose a few
years ago.
And those people that are in these
places, yes, need to have the support
and need to have treatments,
opportunities, supporting places.
Um,
but as they say, you can lead a horse to
water, but you can't make the horse
drink.
But it also goes to say that like maybe
the people who are in those places, who
are on the ground doing those work,
grassroots intervention, etc., who know
the population in those places who are
who who can talk to them and say that
this is where it's needed and how do we
work together in organizing in that in
that way. Um,
I would propose that we can,
since we have enough people here, it
seems like, do we have anyone who is in
favor of just starting with the 200% and
moving forward onto a second
recommendation?
Um, do we have any hands who are in
agreement of the 200%? Please raise your
virtual hand.
Is
there I see five hands up.
>> Okay, I think that's probably about
everybody.
[clears throat]
Oh, we got still some more.
So, we got five five people's hands up.
All right. Is anybody you know would
like to have a different consideration
other than 200%.
Different consideration other than 200%.
So far I only see one hand.
Okay. And I'm just going to say I guess
everyone else is abstaining from voting.
Um,
unless
Don, I can't tell. I saw your hand up
for the for the 200%. I can't tell if
you forgot to lower your hand or if you
were voting for a different
consideration other than 200%.
No comment.
All right. All right. Well, that's half
that's half of the people that are not
um Department of Health,
I guess. Maybe. Do I count? So, that
would be six. Um
okay. So, we have adopted so far that
200% is a starting point. now to work on
a different consideration that we would
have the department or that that we
would have the medical psilocybin
advisory board look at in the next
meeting as far as um
you know our recommendations. Well, I
mean this is going to take an ongoing
conversation so it's it's not going to
go automatically to the board. But
>> I'm sorry. Um Don, if you were
interested in commenting, I have allowed
your mic.
Uh yes, I was uh just voting for the
200%.
>> Oh, okay. So then that's seven. No,
that's that's six. That's six. Okay.
Thank you, Don. I appreciate it. Um
okay, Jeff, let's see. I like the idea
of also loosely putting the money in
geographic and qualified condition
brackets to ensure it serves people
everywhere with different conditions and
then re-evaluate every couple of months
or maybe that we will have what we do
that with the half of the money. Okay,
thank you Senator for um pointing that
out. Um
yeah, if if we wanted to have a
conversation about rural
demographics
and how that is taken into consideration
as well.
I I want to say
I may be presumptive in saying this. I
feel like
that
neglecting for the sake of conversation
that this is already for a qualifying
person
that is
uh
I don't want to say the severity of the
of their of their need but let's just
say for the severity and the sake of the
need that it's already a given. We don't
have to worry about them uh whether like
they've already been okayed and
qualified. Now all we're looking at is
just the criteria for who of those
people who are qualified, let's just say
there's 10 of them, 10 very great
candidates for this program. They meet
all the criteria. The only thing that
we're looking at so far is their
financial uh need. We kind of already
covered that. And then the next one
would be what are we looking at where
they live? Are we looking at that they
um do they have insurance? Are we
looking at the fact that maybe they
don't have insurance? Because that to me
was be like a huge
um
qualifier perhaps. I don't know if
anyone agrees with me. I want to say
that up until [laughter]
just the beginning of this month, I did
not have any insurance. Um, and I
finally bit the bullet and did on the
computer and I was able to to get my
insurance.
Um, there's a lot of fear in trying to
put yourself into the system. Um, so
what are we looking at for the second
qualifying reason that someone is going
to be able to take funds from um, our
equity fund? Any suggestions? I I would
say whether or not they have insurance.
Period.
Even though I feel like no one has an
excuse to have insurance. I just outed
myself and said I did not have any up
until this point up until earlier this
year. So Ian,
>> yeah, I don't think we should um like
exclude people without insurance. If you
don't have insurance, that is that
happens unfortunately in this country
all over. Um, it's why I brought up
earlier, um, my point about what the
medicine would be if I didn't have
insurance because one day it might be
too expensive. Like my state stepped in,
um, and ensured that my premiums
wouldn't go up, but there not everyone
in the country can say that. Um,
and then on just as a side note, I have
held a health insurance producer license
and I still can't understand. So I can
only imagine
uh trying to pick out of the options. It
is horrendous. So yeah, we should
definitely take people who shouldn't who
don't have insurance. Um but I think if
you do have insurance, you have to like
tell us cuz we we want to save as much
money as we can. Um so if you do have
it, great. Tell us. We'll run whatever
we can through it. Um and then if you
don't, obviously we'll step in.
I think I saw Brenda's hand. Thank you,
Ann.
>> But yeah, I agree that people without
insurance should have this. Um, however,
um, there's other things too in the
logistics of things. It's like, okay, so
we, let's say we, uh, one of the, one of
the 10 doesn't have insurance and needs
to have the, um, have the medical check
and haven't had a medical check in quite
some time.
So would that also cover um would the
fund also cover you know their physical
checkup and uh just to make sure that
you know they're they're you know
they're physically able to uh qualify as
well. So that should also be in
um paying for a physician for that
person to get a a checkup too. So yeah,
that would um it could run into being
very expensive. However, um
but also too, would that leave the
person on the hook if they get
disqualified if their medical condition
is not favorable? So that's another
thing we got to look at, I think.
>> Oh gosh, Brenda, thank you so much for
bringing that up. And again, I apologize
to the Department of Health for bringing
even more conversation to it, but I
think it's really helpful. I definitely
know people who are 50 years old and
have never been to the doctor and
probably carried insurance for the last
year and in that time have tried to get
a doctor and failed because the system
is not favorable to finding your
establishing your primary care physician
and then they want you to be just on the
tellaalth and then they lose your tests
and then they charge you for tests that
never even got taken. So,
you know, for anybody who either does
not have insurance, does not have, if
we're looking at the people who may or
may not need it most, it's not the
people essentially, sometimes even who
are who are asking for it, right?
Sometimes the people may be the ones who
don't know that this is even an option.
who don't know that this is even an
option and who are you know maybe they
don't want to but maybe just on a whim
and are able to come in I don't know
exactly who the criteria of the people
and you know God is leading them to to
come to the services but it's you know
who are the people who are who exactly
like Brenda is saying is like have never
had that checkup to know that they have
markers for cancer who have markers for
this and that um and then that's a
holding up a whole whole other, you
know, they go in for their mental health
and realize that they have this whole
other system of issues that need to be
dealt with first and prior to
when things start getting a little bit
more interesting. Um, I don't want to
table that, but I want to just be aware
of that's like a really good
consideration. I feel maybe it's a
little bit too much for the conversation
right now. Um, but my whole point with
the insurance is making sure that
especially the people who don't have it
are the ones who qualify, not to
disqualify them for not having
insurance. Um, but you know, again, it's
just like I don't even why would I even
be I'm thinking in terms of someone who
doesn't have insurance, has never been
to the doctor, who has kind of like this
is going on. Um, and not even knowing
that psilocybin is an option for
treating something that has been
plaguing me all my life or because I am
the victim of uh a sexual assault and I
had no one to talk to, etc. I don't know
what the circumstances are for someone
to come in um and and and feel like that
there is no option or there is no hope,
right? It's not for me to say what that
is, but I'm I'm coming at it from that
perspective of of you know, how do we
how do we reach and sometimes it's not
even the people who think that they want
this. It's for the people who may not
even know that it's an option. Um
okay,
half an hour left. [laughter]
any more possibilities of coming up with
a recommendation?
Um,
yes, let me just read this really
quickly here. Uh,
that goes for therapy as this is from
Brenda. That goes for therapy as well. A
therapist will need to qualify them for
a mental health therapy assessment. Yes.
Uh Jim, legislative action to allow
patients home use access is the simple
solution to using our existing pressure.
We are not there yet. [laughter]
It's a very valid question. It's a very
valid comment. We are not there yet.
This is specifically strictly for the
pathway of medical psilocybin in a
qualified setting with qualified and
certified practitioners and therapists
etc. That is the whole purpose of why we
are here. define pathways in this
specific scope.
Ian,
>> yeah, I just wanted to say that um I'm
not too concerned about the like
different like if they had to find a
doctor and the program had to say,
"Okay, we need your um diagnostics.
We'll pay for it." Cuz realistically,
that should be like 15 minutes of
assumption time if you had any other um
type of experience, right? cuz if um we
are taught at least in nursing and I
hope in most fields to give great
deference to the other medical
professionals. So if for instance a
social worker or clinical counselor sent
in a thing saying hey um we need to uh
this patient I got a fax this patient
has PTSD I'm not going to question it.
I'm not going to be like well this I
don't trust you know their school or
their whatever. I'm going to obviously
do my own assessment and check in. But
generally,
we don't challenge another person,
especially if they were just coming to
me for to essentially say, "Hey, I just
need a non a list that this person has
no contraindications."
Okay. No, thank you for bringing that
up. Um, yeah, and that's kind of, you
know, as coming at it from a massage
therapist, you know, I'm also taking
into consideration what the person on my
table or about to get on my table has
said, as well as, you know, that they
have talked to whatever issue that
they're saying that they have or don't
have um and that they talked to their
medical provider about such issues and
contraindications prior to to working
with me. Um,
let's see. Okay. Is there another
potential proposal of like something to
look at whether it's rural initi a rural
initiative, whether it's um
child care? I know that's a little bit
off the bat, but is there anything else
that we or should consider to look at or
even as uh Senator Steinborn had
reiterated from a previous meeting about
um
and I hate I'm going to say it even
though it sounds horrible, limiting the
number of patients in a specific
diagnosis.
Let's just say and I don't know I don't
want to list off any actual diagnosis
but you know anxiety disorder um and
I've heard uh treat uh treatment uh
depression
resistant therapy um etc. Um would we
limit it to the number of people given
in a specific rural area? I mean we it's
in theory we could stack on as many
uh thresholds gateways as possible you
know but of course it's not like we need
to. So Heneifa I see your hand up.
>> Hi good afternoon. Um, I just wanted to
bounce back to something I left in the
chat earlier, which was around, you
know, should we consider a
recommendation around automatically
qualifying those who are already on
Medicaid uh here in New Mexico?
>> Okay, I think that's a good one. I think
that would probably be a good one.
And Greg,
if you I'm sorry. Hey, Anifa, are you
are you complete?
>> I am complete. Thank you so much.
>> Okay. Uhhuh. And Greg,
[clears throat]
>> I have opinions on the like
categorization. Um, I think it's I think
it's definitely worth
considering. I think if we're going to
do it now ahead of the program data,
it's just like it's arbitrary. Um I
think it would be more valuable to
analyze um
once we have program data analyze uh
what is that what is the term I'm
looking for like um condition type
interaction like the the frequency with
which each condition is being engaged
and try to um kind of align our
percentages based on actual real usage.
I think with the first half a million
dollars or whatever, it's just going to
be like we want to make sure it all gets
spent and if we do put categories on it,
we want to make sure that we can shift
them based on need, which also means
that we're going to be actively
analyzing spending. So like I think uh
Senator Steinborn was talking about like
quarterly reviews of spending and stuff
like that which is going to be like I
don't know if that's going to be a task
for this group or another designated
like department office or whatever but
um I kind of think that it's like too
early to do that categorization like
let's just make sure that people
like we want people to use this. We
don't know how many people are going to
get in. If we see a mob at the front of
the door, maybe we will pause and
reassess quickly. Maybe we have um
optional plans in place. Um but back to
the Medicaid thing, if you're on
Medicaid, you probably have certain
qualifications that put you in the
categories of all the other stuff. So,
making sure we map all that out and
try to find ways for people beyond the
fund, find ways to create equity and
access through the other tools available
to us
before people hit the fund.
Maybe we could even use the fund to
create a team of people that produce a
type of service that helps people who
don't have insurance get insurance. cuz
if you don't have insurance, you can
probably get Medicaid. And the years
that I was I've been without medical
insurance is usually because I'm too
depressed to figure it out. So those
people definitely need help.
And uh yeah, good luck one day.
>> Thank you, Greg, for for um essentially
pointing that out. I too feel like you
know there are a lot of um barriers
towards taking care of ourselves and you
know we and and it's it's it's uh it's
very helpful and I think that was
actually a really great idea. Um
hopefully is Senator Steinborn still
online? um we can take note of that that
I think that would actually be a really
good use of potential funds in the
future should we get some andor for any
other services or people who have the
wherewithal to create such things you
know within specifically for this you
know it's like hey give me I don't want
to say like a list and this is actually
going to happen but you know who are the
people that have applied and you know
are and not have insurance I know that
there are laws with certain things um I
think Brenda you I saw you had your hand
Yeah, thanks. Uh, thanks Desba. So, I
think what we're looking at too is uh
case management to navigate uh any types
of insurance or non-insured people um is
is one thing. Case managers are just
vital in in so many things here in New
Mexico. [gasps] Also too, our resources
are some resources are not as easy to
find. For instance, um uh transportation
often times I,
uh I hear from my clients how hard it is
for them to get transportation from
their home to their doctor to make
appointments. There is there are things
there. Um, I think uh uh Medicare or
Medicaid, either one of those pays for
some type of transportation.
Uh, so our resources are really limited.
When I hear people from Colorado that
move here and they need resources, a lot
of people move back to Colorado or where
they came from to get uh resources that
are just like everyday things in their
states where here in New Mexico. Uh we
don't have um that infrastructure that
needs to be created for many people uh
in uh that are at poverty level. So, you
know, there's there's things that we
have to almost
I I don't want to say for the program
itself because I think there are
limitations of what we can do. Of
course, we want the moon. We want to
lasso it and we want to bring it down
here. However, it it's um it it it is a
lot to take on and we're not going to be
able to provide
uh everything to everyone. And I think
we need to be more realistic about that.
>> Yes.
It's um
that's why I'm trying to with you know I
think I think it I think what I'm going
to say is that I I really like the idea
that one of the second criteria is
looking at Medicaid. Um, and I will ask
for any further discussion on that and
or if there isn't, you know, that's like
a minute after I ask. Um, but I'm going
to go to Hanifeh. I saw your hand pop
up.
>> Yes, thank you again. Um, I think I
heard there's there's two things kind of
emerging, which was if people are
insured, if they don't have insurance,
and then if they are Medicaid recipients
already. Um that's two [clears throat]
two of the other things we consider um
in terms of eligibility. The other thing
was it's just I'm curious about the
capacity of the actual department in
terms of um
you know who
just how they will be sort of reviewing
the the the the applicants that come in
and just wondering you just want to be
careful you know as we're lifting off as
Brenda said just about the capacity of
the department to do a good job you know
in terms of tracking and getting
applications responded to in time and if
are adding a lot of factors. I just it's
just going to add more time and money to
their budget and you know people power
and so I I think this notion of um
divvying up or having some way that
we're um monitor monitoring which
conditions
uh potent applicants are applying for. I
at this stage in the game I would I
would not recommend that. I I think it's
interesting. I think in time um for for
this first round, I do think there's
going to be enough barriers to this to
to accessing this already. And I if
people are showing up and they go
through the whole process and they
qualify, I don't want to turn them away
because oh, we already have the quota
for, you know, PTSD, so good luck next
time. Like I I just I just don't think
that's the way to go for now.
>> I hear you on that, Hipa. Thank you. Are
you done? Sorry. Are you complete?
Yep. I'm done.
>> Okay. Um Okay. Thank you for that. Um I
think what I'm going to propose is to as
as far as like that second
recommendation that Dominic has
requested that we kind of get to by the
end of today. I will record I will see
that both non-insured and Medicaid
recipients
immediately qualify for use of the funds
as a consideration recommendations to be
brought for
uh to the uh advisory board
that both Medicaid recipients and those
who are non-insured
um in favor of that please raise your
hand unless Ian did you have something
to say real
Yeah. Um, so Medicaid kind of comes as
like a subsidy based on income
typically. So are we going to match like
the subsidy and say we'll pay for this
percentage or are we just saying if you
qualify for any Medicaid subsidy then we
will cover the entire thing.
[gasps]
>> I think this is a good question. I think
that the nuance of figuring that out, I
think this is like I'm seeing this as
layers of
these are the first two layers. This
isn't necessarily like the only two
qualifiers
for that.
Um I'm seeing this as like the first two
layers you know the you meeting the
criteria at 200% then the next layer is
Medicaid and um non-insured within those
like if we're doing like a flowchart
right it's 200% then there's like in
non-insured and Medicaid recipients then
underneath those would be other possible
criteria that need to be met andor
considered um And and then from there we
can go into say percentages of what
amount based. So like for instance if it
if a medic 200% was met and their
Medicaid recipient
then what we're looking at say is a
$10,000 treatment for
the medicine plus an additional
$10,000 for therapy sessions. and I'm
I'm I'm splitting them with the medicine
therapy session itself and then the
talking therapy session. So, it's like
$20,000,
then we would kind of go into how much
of that percentage of the 20% based off
of how much Medicaid would be paying for
that. If Medicaid paid for
or let's see, sorry, [laughter]
[gasps]
$19,000,
$900.
And so then the person was able to only
pay for 100 and their co-ay was like 30,
then that means then from the fund is
like 70 bucks. This is this is don't
quote me on this, but I'm just saying
that like I feel like we'll get to the
actual ins and outs of how that is
actually being used, but for now to me
the layer is 200% Medicaid and and
non-insured. If I'm getting this false,
please Dominic, speak up or hold your
peace.
Um um let's see. Hanifa, you have a
question.
Let's see who I'm sorry I can't see
everybody's
sorry it was Greg first. Greg, sorry.
>> No, if anybody can go in front of me,
it's fine. I totally lost my train of
thought.
>> Okay.
>> Um, thank you. I I I think that the way
I'm envisioning this is like 200% is
kind of what we're starting off as like
the baseline, right? To me, if someone's
uninsured or is already a Medicaid
recipient, um it's like in a different c
it's like a different category, right?
Because some people won't have Medicaid
or won't be Medicaid recipients and so
we'd be looking at that 200%.
So, what I'm saying Medicaid is that
it's just I I just feel like people who
are already receiving Medicaid or do not
have insurance
um and they right have the bar of they
have a qualifying condition, etc.
should be con, you know, they should be
able to apply, you know,
>> kind of automat automatically um without
necessarily having to show the 200%
particular Medicaid showing that they
have the 200% um you know that they're
under that they're at that level because
Medicaid
>> should determine that already. Does that
make sense?
>> Okay. Yeah. No, I think that I think
part of my explanation in that is me not
understanding the qualifications for the
Medicaid, etc. I know that I I don't
qualify, so I to me it's all voodoo
voodoo economics and math when it comes
to some of this stuff. Um, so I
apologize for a lack of understanding
exactly about the 200%. But it's just I
want to say either way, it's these two
qualifying things that we're going to
look at and then we can kind of go into
uh exactly how that might
um be more
defined in the future. But at least this
is a place to start and then we can
start filling in
different analogy that may or may not
work. Filling that mayonnaise jar with
the stones. These are the first two big
stones and then we can start filling in
>> the rest of that mason jar with the rest
of the things that are important. So
right now these are the two big things
that are important for qualifying people
for the medical psilocybin therapy
program.
>> Right. Can I just say one more thing is
that
>> due to to Ian's point or question then
like you're saying Desba then you get
into figuring because Medicaid isn't
going to cover the medicine session. So
even though someone has Medicaid, we
still have to figure out what percentage
is there are they going to cover for the
prep and integration and then you know
are they going to get one session or two
treatment sessions etc. So even if they
are Medicaid qual Medicaid recipients
the payment of the medicine session
still has to be worked out and that's
what the fund would be helping to cover.
>> Yeah. So it's like how do you even how
do we even get in the door is those who
are 200% you know we the door that they
entered in first was having a qualifying
medical diagnosis for a treatment of
medical psilocybin then the next door is
like do you have to for the for the fund
for the fund is you know do you are you
200% poverty level or below then they go
in through that door are you also a
Medicaid recipient then they also go in
through the door then from there we kind
of just did. So it really is kind of
like
you know the Panama Canal asia I'm not
sure as we're going down the stream for
to trying to figure out how we then
allocate the money at the end and yeah
some people are going to be
you know essentially left at the door um
which is not how we'd like to do things
but those are kind of like the facts. Um
I think in did I hear see your hand pop
up again?
>> I think I'm next Gregory Okay,
[laughter] I'm
>> just gonna jump in here because I can't
stop thinking about a jar of rocks. Just
want to like sit with that for a minute.
It's beautiful.
It can be the program logo.
Um,
it's a cart and horse thing. It's it's
really strange cuz it's like you got to
go to the doctor to get the designation
and then you have to but then like there
may be a real need for a treatment plan
to be in place like to say hey with your
provider before you even go to the um
qualifying condition the officer
whatever the what are we calling that
qualifying clinician certifying
clinician um [clears throat]
that treatment plan might already be in
place which means that you've actually
interacted acted with this provider to
some context, whether it's billable
hours or consulting hours that they do
to get people in the door or something
like that.
But then if you're billing the entire
thing, I I'm I should just look this up,
but there's a term for when you bill for
treatment as total in a single insurance
event. So that treatment plan would be
required for that billing structure. So
you're not just like, I went to I went
to this therapy and it qualifies as
this. went to this therapy and equalizes
this and have individual bills, you're
looking at billing for the entire
context of the therapy. Um
[clears throat] then back to the
taking this back to the purpose of the
immediate task at hand which is voting
on the um qualifying. I wanted to ask if
it was the intent to autoqualify or
streamline qualification for access to
equity funds by just having like I've
already gone through the process of
getting Medicaid. So, I've proven my
insurance or proven my financial need
for this thing. So, then that just kind
of shortens the application process. I
think there will have to be an
application process for to receive funds
or whatever because they're going to
have to come through something. But
yeah, just that container of
autoqualifyish.
>> Yes,
I hear what you're saying. I believe
what I'm understanding is just like is
this the only two qualifying things in
order to have access to the treatment?
And I am not I I don't believe so. This
is my understanding. what it sounds like
streamline. Yes, perhaps that then they
go to the next
level. It's like playing Candy Crush or
whatever it is, you know, you go to the
next level because you qualified for
this and now you can go on to the next.
It could also be depending on whether or
not this is the recommendation of the
board or the committee that yes, these
are the only two qualifying signatures.
We've done our duty. you know, we're
we've we figured it out and so now it's
on to the to the board. We could have
further discussion
and we know that like at the end of the
day our recommendations and our best
practices might fall into those two
categories, recommendations or best
practices and that's you know that's but
all we can do is deliberate what we feel
is like in the best interest of the
entire state of two million people in
New Mexico. um you know for the sake of
having access to $630,000 for a medical
psilocybin treatment program um in
>> Yeah. So I wanted to bring up two
things. Um or actually just one. The
maybe it would be pertinent for the
department to on like the license for um
a healing center type of operation to
report their what they are charging for
customers um or patients. That's way we
can know what the cost of service is at
a regulatory level and get those
statistics. Um then we could tie in like
average cost kind of thing um if that
were necessary. Um
or like other options that way we just
have more data for our analysis. Um
and yeah, that was pretty much my
recommendation was just to collect that
when they're getting their lensure. Um,
in insurance, uh, the insurance
companies have to file with the state
their premiums, their discounts, why
they're doing certain things. That way,
they can't just make up a price on the
spot. Um, so maybe we have something
similar where I don't want what I don't
want to happen is someone to get charged
a higher price because they are using
the equity fund.
Yes, I hear what you're saying, which is
kind of it's not the reason why I said
like it's just a set price in universal
health healthcare. It was just like, you
know, the treatment itself, the the
medicine session itself is just across
the board, no matter what a therapist
charges $235 for a session or $500 or
$1,000 for their session for the talking
part, just strictly for the psilocybin,
etc. might end up being like whatever.
And I don't know that that actually
really helped. That's the reason why I
said, you know, it's like it can't be
charged over this amount for for this
particular thing because we also need to
propagation cultivation people. They
also need to be able to be paid
appropriately for their work. Um, we
have eight minutes left. I will get to
Senator Steinborn in just a minute, but
I know that we're going to have to kind
of come up with a meeting for the next I
if anybody on the Department of Health
can look at the weeks I think of the for
the week before Indie Market um and
after Indie Market in August if there's
any dates in there that look like
they're more favorable um for the next
meeting. And Senator Steinborn, did you
want to go ahead and say something?
Sure.
Thank you. Um I just I'm curious, you
know, we we've thrown a lot out there if
uh Dominic and company have any kind of
initial feedback on
kind of what feels workable to you? Is
there anything that really resonates or
that you would offer up as advice or do
you want to just process it and not kind
of commit to anything right now and then
come back to us? I just want to hear
from you guys.
>> Thank you, Senator. Uh, I appreciate it
and and I think there there's been a lot
of points that have been raised today
and a lot of them that we've been
considering for the last several months
and um but I do think that right now it
it is one of those situations where it's
a very complex set of um you know it's a
complex set of circumstances and there's
a lot of aspects to be to be considered
and so uh right now I think that just
sitting with those to sort of hear and
it's a part of why we've asked what are
the recommendations from the committee
because we want to hear from people to
see what people think is going to be
most workable. Some parts that we think
would be most important may not
necessarily be from a community
standpoint. We want to ensure that we
consider what the community wants as
well. And I say that as though it's one
unified community. We also realize that
it's actually many uh smaller
communities making up a larger
community, but we really do want to hear
what the different ideas are and
potential recommendations. So, I mean,
with that, that's a long-winded way of
saying we really do want to sit with it
for a little bit to try to determine
what would work. Well,
>> let me ask this one little question if
we have time. Desa, just one final
question. is Dominic, do you guys have
the capacity to integrate a few little
variables such as you know what other
are are they covering other aspects of
the journey that are able to be covered
by insurance or you know separating the
money into different buckets at all just
to see kind of what's available to
ensure that there's not a run on it
right off the bat. Uh do you have that
capacity? Do you have enough staff or
where are you at with capacity?
>> Well, I I think it really depends in
part on uh what happens in this next
session as far as the ongoing funding
for the program. Um I if uh if things go
well then I think we would indeed have
that capacity. Um so that we would be
you know we would be able to parse out
some of those different aspects of it to
be able to determine what's workable,
what's not. Um but as it has kind of has
been brought up by different people at
different points on it, we also you know
there's also a certain aspect of it that
we don't want to be big brother. We
don't need to know everybody's the
intimate details of everybody's
financial, you know, uh situation. And
so I think there are some things we can
do that can help reduce some of that
burden. Um and so we'll continue to work
on that uh once we actually have the
recommendations and start crafting it
into a set of regulations and really
protocols and it will always be
something that we look at up to. It's
not going to be a guarantee that we
would we would be able to fund all of
somebody's treatment. Um it may be that
there need to be limitations. With that
in mind, we also know that when
insurance companies, for example, put
limitations on say number of sessions of
therapy, that ends up becoming the de
facto maximum number of sessions. So, we
have to keep that sort of thing in mind,
but the money is finite as you've
mentioned and um we need to make sure
that we're able to help as many people
as we possibly can including those as I
think it's Jim who mentioned it, but
including those who need it the most.
So,
uh we'll we'll continue to to to process
through this and figure out how to do
it. It's it's never an easy process when
we're looking at equity issues.
>> Thank you, Senator Seyorn and uh Dominic
for having that last little kind of
conversation. So, we were not able to
really kind of get to the second
recommendation that we might have from
here, but I just kind of want to put a
little pin in this idea of Medicaid. I
think that that was another potential
consideration. Um, you know, it's
important to look at the rural
transportation needs of people. Um, and
although we do not want to, this is what
I'm hearing, we do not want to uh limit
different kinds of qualifying medical uh
needs as to who can have access to what.
Um, but that it is might be something to
have an awareness of in the future. Um
but that the goal of this is really just
to kind of find a place that we can
uh move forward step by step by step by
step. So this is just like the first
step. We have many steps to go but we
can do it one step at a time. Um did we
have a potential dates in um August the
weeks before a uh let's see sorry let me
go to August. I think it's the week of
August 10th or the week is August 24th
that we're kind of favorable for the
department.
>> That's uh the Indian market is uh August
14th through the 16th. Right. But
there's events leading up to it to that
week. Uh I imagine like Right. Right. So
yeah, the the week of the 3rd through
the 7th is beforehand. Uh is there a
specific day?
>> Yeah. So sorry, I forgot that it's the
weekend. I'm always thinking it's the
week. So it's like the 17th and the
24th. Those two weeks that are probably
more favorable. The 17th and the 24th.
>> Any So, okay. So, you're saying not
before Indian market but at the week
following. Correct.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Clarify because usually there's
stuff the week before. [snorts]
>> Uh is there a day of the week that you
prefer? I would say that like the 18th
uh August Tuesday, just keeping it on a
Tuesday, the 18th or the 25th is fine
for me.
>> Mhm. [clears throat] Yes. Uh we do have
>> 3:00
>> 3:00. Uh that does work on Tuesday the
18th.
>> Okay.
>> Of August.
>> All right.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Sounds good.
Thank you very much.
>> Thank you all. Is there any closing
things? Dominic Jorge, any departmental
admin, please send comments to medical
psilocybin dooh.n.gov.
Um, please continue the discussion
amongst yourselves [laughter] in spaces.
And again, thank you so much for your
time and spending some time with me this
afternoon. And just thank you everybody
as usual a very rich conversation and
it's very helpful for us. So thank you
all. Hope you all have a great rest of
the day.